{"tossups": [{"question": "This system was allegedly exploited when Justinian successfully sent spies disguised as Christian monks to steal eggs. Thanks to the missions of Zhang Qian, this system was greatly expanded. Stops known as caravanserais helped service this system. Glassware and gold coins honoring Antoninus Pius were exchanged for textiles along this route, which connected Europe with Asia. For ten points, identify this Chinese trade route cultivated by the Han dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Silk Road</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The death of this empire\u2019s founding ruler Digha Ciss\u00b4e caused a power struggle between his sons Khine and Dyabe; when Dyabe lost, he legendarily sacrificed a virgin to the snake Bida every year until he died. Al-Bakri wrote of dogs with golden collars in this empire, whose original Soninke name was Wagadou. Controlling the salt and gold trade across the Sahara, this empire was later absorbed by Mali. For ten points, the Gold Coast is presently named for what medieval West African empire?", "answer": "<b> Ghana</b> (or<b> Wagadou</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city feuded with the Ercole d\u2019Este [AIR-co-lay DES-tay] to protect its salt-mining rights in the Commachio in the Ferrara War. This city guarded one aspect of its trade by preventing its glassmakers from leaving Murano. This city\u2019s conquest of Dalmatia was celebrated by this city every Ascension Day, where the ship Bucentaur would go out to sea and a ring would be dropped into the water. The Marriage of the Sea ritual took place in, for ten points, what Italian \u201cserene republic\u201d that was led by a doge?", "answer": "<b> Venice</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Robert Landsburg died taking photographs of this event and, in his last moments, laid on top of his backpack to protect its contents. For ten points, name this 1980 in which a volcano in Washington erupted. David Johnston radioed \u201cVancouver! Vancouver! This is it!\u201d before dying during this event despite being over six miles away. The destruction of camps around Spirit Lake as part of this event resulted in the death of Harry R. Truman. For ten points, name this 1980 event in which the eruption of a Washington volcano decimated the surrounding area.", "answer": "the<b> eruption</b> of Mount<b> St. Helens</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Jules Michelet gave the first definition of this period in his<em> History of France</em>. Jakob Burkhardt argued that this period gave birth to modern individuality in<em> The Civilization of [this period]</em>. This period\u2019s reputation for cultural advancement has been challenged by historians who emphasize its nostalgia for classicism and continuity with the Middle Ages. For ten points, name this era usually characterized by the flourishing of art and humanism in 15th and 16th century Italy.", "answer": "The<b> Renaissance</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Under this man\u2019s Personalist government, members of the ruling Can Lao party were originally told to keep their memberships secret. This leader reorganized 14,000 villages into \u201cstrategic hamlets\u201d in order to secure backing from the countryside. This leader\u2019s unpopularity grew after launching a series of raids on the Xa Loi Pagoda. His downfall was precipitated by the self-immolation of Buddhist monk Thich Quang Duc. For ten points, identify this American-backed president of South Vietnam.", "answer": "Ngo Dinh<b> Diem</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A parable from this work titled \u201cThe Eldest Lady\u2019s Tale\u201d is likely an early Cinderella story. A caliph finds a dead body in a chest in a section of this work titled \u201cThe Three Apples.\u201d In this work, the slave-girl Morgiana saves her master by pouring boiling oil on thieves hidden in jars. Stories in this collection feature historical figures like Khosrow II and Harun al-Rashid. For ten points, name this collection of stories that features the characters Sinbad the Sailor and Ali Baba.", "answer": "<b> Arabian Nights</b> (accept<b> One Thousand and One Nights</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "In this state, William Fishback helped pass an amendment that banned payment of Holford Bonds. A political family in this state formed after Robert Crittenden broke dueling etiquette. The Conway-Johnson family operated in this state where Joseph Brooks and Elisha Baxter started a \u201cwar\u201d for the governorship. The refusal of Orval Faubus to allow integrated schools in this state led Dwight Eisenhower to send in the national guard. For ten points, name this state where, in 1957, nine black students were enrolled in Little Rock Central High School.", "answer": "<b> Arkansas</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A pectoral found in this place with a red disk and a blue beetle represents the prenomen of one person in this place, which was discovered when a water boy stumbled on a stone. This place\u2019s treasury contained a gold-covered canopic chest and the remains of two stillborn children. One object found in this place has quartz and obsidian eyes and an elongated gold and lapis lazuli beard. That mask was found in, for ten points, what tomb, officially named KV62, discovered by Howard Carter in the Valley of Kings?", "answer": "The<b> Tomb</b> of<b> Tut</b>enkhamun (accept<b> KV62</b> before mention)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Two answers required.</em> One of these two countries implemented Operation Streamline to control illegal immigrants from the other during the early-2000s. The Chamizal dispute clarified the border between these two countries, which is the most commonly crossed border in the world. Yuma and Nogales were added to one country after the Gadsden Purchase modified these two countries\u2019 border. For ten points, name these two countries in the Western Hemisphere whose planned border wall has been a source of controversy since 2016.", "answer": "<b> U</b>nited<b> S</b>tates and<b> Mexico</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "The pagan god Baal became known as Belos, which was later translated as the name of this Greek deity. Israel targeted Iran with a cyber-attack project named after \u201cNitro\u201d and this deity. The continent of Europe was named after a lady who was kidnapped by this deity. For ten points, name this son of Rhea and Cronus, known as Jupiter to the Romans, who became the king of the Greek gods and wielder of lightning bolts.", "answer": "<b> Zeus</b> (do not accept or prompt on \u201cJupiter\u201d)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Much of this present-day state was explored by Gaspar de Portola who expelled its Jesuits in 1767. Francis Drake landed in this modern-day state during his circumnavigation, claiming it as New Albion for the English. Juan Cabrillo was the first European to navigate the coast of this modern state, whose Baja and Alta sub-regions are divided between Mexico and the United States. For ten points, name this West Coast state where Spanish missions evolved into cities like San Francisco.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This house originated after Ren\u00b4e of Chalon died in battle, leaving another ruler to add the title of a French principality to this house. A military strategist from this house won the Battle of Turnhout and was named Maurice. Members of this family did not rule during the First Stadtholderless Period. Wilhelmina from this house technically was the last of its male line and became a symbol of the resistance during WWII. For ten points, name this royal house which names the current Dutch ruling family.", "answer": "House of<b> Orange</b>-Nassau", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Simon Sterne questioned this company\u2019s leadership as part of the Hepburn Committee. John Dustin Archbold served as the primary spokesman for this company in which role he survived a 1915 assassination attempt by the IWW. This company is the subject of a work whose final chapter, \u201cThe Compromise of 1889\u201d, explores how it silenced organized opposition and individual complaint. Ida Tarbell wrote a history of this company exposing their lie about supporting independent pipelines. John D. Rockefeller founded, for ten points, what often corrupt oil company?", "answer": "<b> Standard Oil</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "While departing Sicily, this leader said \u201cWhat a wrestling ground we are leaving, my friends, for the Carthaginians and the Romans.\u201d This enemy of Antigonus II Gonatas died after being hit in the head by a tile thrown by an old woman in Argos. This ally of Tarentum used elephants to win the Battle of Heraclea and his forces were later weakened despite winning the Battle of Asculum. Victories with unsustainably heavy costs to the victor are named after, for ten points, what Epirote general?", "answer": "<b> Pyrrhus</b> of Epirus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>An opera by this composer features arias from two unhappily married couples sung during a game of bridge. This composer set 10 old Irish poems in his</b><em><b> Hermit Songs</b></em><b>. This composer\u2019s (+)</b><em><b> Capricorn</b></em><b> Concerto is named for a house he lived in with his partner Gian Carlo Menotti. This composer set a text by James Agee in his (*)</b><em> Knoxville: Summer of 1915</em>. This composer\u2019s own adaptation of the second movement of his string quartet, also set as a choral<em> Agnus</em> <em>Dei</em>, was broadcast over the radio after FDR\u2019s death. For ten points, name this composer of<em> Adagio for</em> <em>Strings</em>.", "answer": "Samuel<b> Barber</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Agent A-54 was a double agent in the Abwehr for this nation. A leader of this nation published \u201cRacial Problems in Hungary\u201d and fought Jewish blood libels in the Hilsner Case. (+) Emil Hacha led this country as a Protectorate. The \u201cFourth Plan\u201d was proposed by this country\u2019s leader Edvard (*) </b> Benes, who passed decrees to expel ethnic Germans. This country\u2019s defenses were crippled after Britain and France forced it to give Sudetenland to Nazi Germany. The Munich Agreement targeted, for ten points, what no longer extant country that was governed from Prague?", "answer": "<b> Czechoslovakia</b> (prompt on \u201cProtectorate of Bohemia and Moravia,\u201d do not accept or prompt on Czech Republic or Slovakia)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man served as Mormaer of Moray and defeated his predecessor in his highest position at Bothnagowan before himself being killed at Lumphanan. This man\u2019s reign was chronicled by John of Fordun, but the most famous account of this person is based on (+) Holinshed\u2019s Chronicles. In that account, he is told he can\u2019t be killed by anyone born of a woman\u2019s womb by (*) </b> three witches, only to fall to the Thane of Fife, who was born by Caesarian section. Malcolm III succeeded, for ten points, what Scottish king whose actual reign was more successful than depicted in a namesake Shakespeare tragedy?", "answer": "<b> Macbeth</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A 1980</b><em><b> Boston Globe</b></em><b> article about this man had the accidental, but humorous, headline\u201cMush from the Wimp.\u201d</b><em><b> The Washington Post</b></em><b> created a political cartoon parodying Jaws, creatively named PAWS, to mock this man after he was \u201cattacked\u201d by a (+) swamp rabbit. This man challenged the notion that \u201cThere is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe\u201d in a debate with (*)</b> Gerald Ford. This President ordered the disastrous Operation Eagle Claw, a failed attempt to end the Iran-Hostage Crisis. For ten points, name this oft-mocked President who only served one term after being elected in 1976.", "answer": "Jimmy<b> Carter</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One regiment from this country was annihilated during an offensive at Beaumont-Hamel. A memorial designed by Walter Seymond Allwell stands on Hill 145, which was taken by an assault by this country\u2019s forces in a battle sometimes called \u201cThe Birth of\u201d this nation</b> <b>at (+)</b> <b>Vimy Ridge. The Third Battle of Ypres was ended when Arthur Currie led forces</b> <b>from this country to capture (*)</b> Passchendaele. In a 1917 Conscription Crisis, this country\u2019s French speakers opposed the Military Service Act and the British war effort. For ten points, name this former Dominion in North America.", "answer": "Dominion of<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In his essay</b><em><b> Beating the Averages</b></em><b>, Paul Graham argues that this programming language is the reason his startup Viaweb was successful. John McCarthy designed this language, which quickly gained popularity in the AI community. Implementations of this language</b> <b>include (+)</b> <b>Clojure, Scheme, and its \u201cCommon\u201d variant. Emacs uses this programming</b> <b>Clojure, Scheme, and its \u201cCommon\u201d variant. Emacs uses this programming</b> <b>language for scripting, and the syntax for this language is all (*)</b> <b>language for scripting, and the syntax for this language is all (*)</b> S-expressions. For ten points, name this second oldest high-level programming language after Fortran, known for using lots of parentheses.", "answer": "<b> Lisp</b> (prompt on \u201cClojure\u201d or \u201cScheme\u201d, accept Common<b> Lisp</b>) Page 10", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}